字幕翻译/压制：旋火
视频来源：youtu.be/p36X2h1opGc
原视频发布日期：20200412
原作者名：Scott Manley
大家好 这里是Scott Manley
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
Paul Allen去世了一年之后 平流层发射系统未来的计划才终于为人所知
Over a year after the death of Paul Alan, Stratolaunch future plans are finally coming into public focus.
Roc指阿拉伯神话中的大鹏
云杉鹅指休斯H-4大力神，于1940年代末生产的水上飞机，最终被废弃
一段时间以来大家认为这个大鹏会变成21世纪版本的云杉鹅
For a while it was assuming that the Roc would become known as the 21st century of the Spruce Goose.
不会把火箭送入太空
Instead of launching Rockets into space,
大鹏反而将会携带一个小型的高超音速火箭动力飞机Talon A
the Roc will instead carry a small hypersonic Rocket plane called the Talon A
这将会是一个进行高超音速实验的商业平台
which will be a commercial platform to perform hypersonic experiments
这看起来是个很有趣的转变
which is something of an interesting transition.
很显然人们对这种高超音速武器很感兴趣
I mean obviously there's been a lot of interest in in hypersonic weapons
也就是能在大气中机动的那种高超音速武器
that maneuver inside the atmosphere.
所以可以预见的是会有很多研发的资金流向这些公司
So it's conceivable that there might be a lot of research money coming out to companies
这些公司可能会想要一个方便的服务
who might want a plug in and play environment
这种服务可以让它们进行各种气流的前沿实验
where they can deploy their experiments on leading-edge in the air stream in various other places.
在这种服务中只需要进行飞行实验 而不需要打造出了一个完整的测试平台
And just fly their experiments rather than having to build out an entire testbed.
所以Talon真的很小
So the Talon is really small.
Talon不到9米长 加满燃料的发射质量少于3吨
It's less than nine meters long and at launch will mass less than three tons fully fueled.
有着三角翼和单尾翼的设计
The design has a delta wing and a single tail.
但这不是我们从平流层发射系统那里听说过的第一个高超音速测试航天器
But this isn't the first we heard about a hypersonic test vehicle from Stratolaunch.
我看到过的一个文件讲过Hyper A的设计 与之相比稍微不同
I've seen a paper talking about the Hyper A which had a slightly different configuration.
它使用的是翼尖小翼
It had wingtip fins instead
它也会使用一种火箭发动机
and it was also gonna use a Rocket engine
这种发动机叫PGA 由平流层发射系统公司设计制造
designed and built by Stratolaunch called the PGA
这将是一种氢氧发动机
that would be a hydrogen oxygen engine.
但是一些访谈或文章透露出
However interviews or articles suggest that
他们现在正在寻找火箭发动机的外部供应商
they're now looking for outside providers for the Rocket engine
我认为Aerojet Rocketdyne的RL-10发动机会是个不错的选择
which I think Aerojet Rocketdyne with their RL-10 might be a good bet
因为他们已经和平流层发射系统交流过了
since they've already been talking with Stratolaunch
但同样也可能因为太过昂贵
but equally that might be too expensive
他们可能从Masten Space Systems这种更小的供应商购买发动机
and they might go with an engine from a smaller provider like Masten Space Systems
而这家公司和平流层发射系统离得很近
who are basically in the same neighborhood as Stratolaunch.
同样是这个文件也展示出了Hyper A风洞模型
The paper in question also shows wind tunnel models off the Hyper A
有一种可能是他们之前已经在开发了
and you know this sort of shows that there is some previous development they've been working on.
这不是你愚人节前面刚糊弄出来
This isn't something that you just threw together just before April 1st
忽悠投资者的东西
to try and convince investors.
这个项目已经有了一些实质性工作
This is something that has had some substantive work and studies being done on it.
那么为了验证它的功能 需要把它带到测试的位置
So the way this would work is it would be carried out to test launch site
因为它需要飞到6马赫的速度
because this is gonna travel at about Mach 6.
这肯定是一个相当长的距离
They have to be a fairly long distance away.
为了做到这一点 它们的试验地点会在加州海岸附近
They would do this off the coast of California.
试验高度从9.144km开始 一路上升至27.432km
it would start at 30, 000 feet and rise up to 90, 000 feet
它的速度将会在几分钟内达到6到7马赫
and at that point it would travel at about your Mach 6 or Mach 7 for a few minutes.
一旦(发动机)停止 它会从那个高度一路滑翔下来并返回莫哈维着陆
And once it stopped, it will glide down from altitude and land back at Mojave.
或者根据不同实验 航天器也可以进行弹道式的飞行
Alternatively depending on the experiment you could also do a ballistic path
如你所知 会飞得尽可能地高
where it would fly up to as high as you know.
在这种情况下可以飞到145.3896km的高度
477, 000 feet in this case.
尽管这种情况下航天器能飞到10马赫
Although this vehicle at this point is supposed to be going at Mach 10
但是这可能将无法代表Talon A的性能
that may not be representative of what Talon A is capable of.
但是平流层发射系统的网站上还列出了这个航天器未来的版本
But the Stratolaunch site also has the future iterations of the vehicle listed.
Talon A是小号的那一个
The Talon A is the small one.
你实际上可以在一个大鹏下面挂载三个这样的航天器
You can actually put three of those on a single Roc.
Talon Z则是下一代的
The Talon Z is the next generation.
它们都是按照大鹏的限制来制造的
They all are built to fit one of these.
事实上 Talon Z在原来的文件中并不存在
In fact while the Talon Z obviously didn't exist in the original paper
有个渲染图展示了放大版的Hyper A
there is a rendering showing a larger version of the Hyper A
所以估计这些航天器的机身大小都差不多
so presumably these things are gonna be roughly comparable in terms of airframe size
所以你只能在大鹏上同时放下一个这样的(大尺寸)航天器
and yeah you're gonna only be able to put one of these on the Roc at a time
看起来好像他们没有完全放弃发射物体入轨的想法
and it looks as if they haven't completely abandoned their idea of launching stuff into orbit
因为他们还列出了Black Ice这样未来会研制的航天器
because they list Black Ice as a future vehicle
这个航天器的大小可以通过它前面那个有着窗户的驾驶舱那个来推测
and you can tell how big this is by the fact that they have a cockpit at the front with windows.
这个大小将会和航天飞机一样
This is gonna be about the same size as a Space Shuttle.
估计能有100吨的质量
Presumably maybe about a hundred tons mass
实际上大鹏可以携带230吨有效载荷，不止100吨，估计是Scott Manley口胡
这将会和大鹏所能携带的质量一致
that would be consistent with what the Roc is able to carry.
所以这不是Talon A会怎么飞的官方动画
So there's no official animations of how the Talon A would actually fly or perform
但是如果我需要动画的时候就可以用这个了
which gives me a perfect excuse as if I needed one
在坎巴拉太空计划(KSP)中尝试制造
to try and build a version in Kerbal Space Program.
很难得到准确的推力数值因为机身太大了
Getting the exact propulsion is kinda hard because the fuselage is way too fat
比现实中平流层发射系统的机身大多了
compared to what Stratolaunch actually uses.
但是你可以粗略得到正确地大小形状
But you can get something that's roughly the right shape and size
并且获得大概正确的高度
and get to approximately the right altitude.
这都是原版组件
Yeah this is all stock.
正如以往一样 驾驶舱放在了左边
And yeah we put the cockpit on the right side sorry the left side as usual
因为驾驶员(一般)在左边
because of course captain's fly on the left.
大鹏将会远远飞离发射场
So the Roc would fly a long way from the launch site
然后转身并把Hyper A指向目标
and turn around and then point the Hyper A at the target.
之后在适当的距离上拉起爬升并释放航天器
Then at the appropriate distance would pull into a climb, release the vehicle
之后它就会点燃发动机并开始爬升到(目标)高度
which would then light its engines and start climbing towards altitude.
在这个设计中它有四个小的火箭发动机
In this design has got four little Rocket engines
看起来像是X-15
so it'll look a little more like X-15
但是他们只会使用一个火箭发动机
but simply they're gonna use a single Rocket engine
或者是两个火箭发动机 这取决于他们的供应商
or perhaps a pair of Rocket engines depending upon their provider.
如果我们相信Hyper A的文件的话
If we are to trust the Hyper A paper
那么在全推力情况下 它的发动机大概能工作90到100秒
then it will get maybe 90-seconds to a 100-seconds of full thrust.
所以一开始它会抬头爬升 然后再放平姿态
So initially it's gonna head up into a climb and then start letting the thing level out
最后会进入一个弧形弹道
so it flies into essentially a ballistic arc
然后就继续这样加速了
and then just continues to accelerate out through this.
在这里你能看到速度只是刚刚过了1马赫
Then you see at this point we're only traveling just over Mach 1 here
所以我们要放平姿态
so we're gonna have to get level
这样就能保持我们需要的速度了
so we can sustain the amount of speed that we actually need.
再说一下 这并不是那么准确
Again this is not really that accurate.
如果这是一个精确的高超音速试验台
If this was an accurate hypersonic test bed,
那么平流层发射系统就没戏了
then Stratolaunch wouldn't have a market
因为他们的客户肯定会去玩KSP了
because their customers would be playing Kerbal Space Program obviously.
即使是使用今天的超级计算机 对这些速度进行流体力学的计算
I mean even with the today's supercomputers you can perform computational fluid dynamics at these speeds
但它需要大量的资源
but it takes a lot of resources
而且现实中有原子氧侵蚀作用
and then you have you erosion * effects
例如化学反应持续发生
where you have for example chemical changes going on
当空气中的原子被冲击得如此剧烈
when the atom in the air is hitting so hard
氧分子分裂为了原子 并且更易发生反应
the oxygen atoms or molecules are breaking into atoms and becoming more reactive.
这就对热力学产生了很大影响
That changes a lot of your thermodynamics.
那么它基本上就是这么飞
So yeah it would basically fly into this
然后改平加速达到它的(最大)速度
and then level out accelerate up to its speed
也可能会在这段时间保持一定的速度
and perhaps it would maintain speed for a while
直到某时 它的燃料耗光了
and at some point it would run out of fuel
然后它就会变成一个滑翔器
and from there it would become a glider.
我控制的这艘飞船的鼻锥差点就要爆炸了
This one I got just right as you can see the nose cone is about to explode
还好在爆炸之前用尽了燃料
but it burns out just before they are.
我觉得我做得不错
And I feel like I did a pretty good job.
当然啦 电脑可以驾驶这个东西
Of course computers would be flying this thing.
我自己开是为了不让电脑享受这个乐趣
I'm flying this myself because I'm gonna let computers have all the fun.
不管怎么说 这个新的高超音速商业平台是一个有趣的概念
So anyway this new hypersonic business platform is an interesting concept.
这对平流层发射系统会是一个好的转折
It's a big turnaround for Stratolaunch.
他们之前花了不少时间把这个飞机搞回来
They've had a heck of a time trying to get a launch vehicle back
当时Vulcan Aerospace原本要把这个飞机卖掉
when Stratolaunch was originally pinched after it was it was like Vulcan aviation I believe or the Vulcan Aerospace.
他们之前要发射一个SpaceX制造的火箭
They were gonna fly with a rocket built by SpaceX.
猎鹰5号像是某种程度上Paul Allen和Elon Musk之间的君子协议
The Falcon 5 was sort of a gentlemen's agreement between Paul Allen and Elon Musk.
但到了某时就明确了
but at some point it was it became clear that
猎鹰5号和猎鹰9号没什么相同的地方 然后开发工作就停止了
the Falcon 5 would have very little in common with the Falcon 9 and the development was stopped.
这让他们又去寻找另一种运载火箭
So that left them looking for another launch vehicle.
下一个他们找上的是轨道ATK的飞马座火箭
The next place they looked was Orbital ATK who of course made the Pegasus.
但是飞马座是一个正在消亡的运载火箭
But the Pegasus is a launch vehicle is dying.
已经没有任何客户想要用它
It doesn't have any customers who want to use it anymore.
2019年10月11日的飞马座XL火箭发射，载荷是ICON
去年它进行的最后一次任务推迟了
The last mission that flew last year was delayed.
指2019年7月猎鹰9号而不是飞马座拿下了NASA的IXPE发射合同
与此同时 确实有一个潜在的为飞马座量身定制的发射机会
And while there was one potential launch opportunity for at one contract that was tailor-made for Pegasus.
这也是由SpaceX公司拿下
That was also won by SpaceX
也就是猎鹰9号会进行发射
who are gonna have to make their Falcon 9 do something.
这并不是一开始所设想的那样
It wasn't really originally envisaged to do.
某次平流层发射系统也讨论过一次发射三个飞马座XL
At one point Stratolaunch was talking about being able to launch three Pegasus XL at once
当然是不会发生的
which yeah it wasn't gonna happen.
一个飞马座XL都没人要
No one was wanting to fly a single Pegasus XL.
更不可能还同时要三个
Nevermind three of them any at the same time.
2018年大鹏已经进行飞机滑行测试
In 2018 the Roc was already performing taxi tests
证明它自个儿能动
to demonstrate that it was able to move under its own power
当时它很快就会进行起飞(测试)
and was only a matter of time before it was going to fly.
那时平流层发射系统宣布
And they announced that
有一堆要计划自己开发的火箭
they had a bunch of their own rocket concepts that Stratolaunch was planning to develop
但是之后Paul Allen去世了
but then Paul Allen died
而Vulcan Ventures背后的新人们不想再继续投资平流层发射系统
and the new people behind Vulcan Ventures were no longer interested in financing it.
Paul Allen的想法很明确
Paul Allen had a very specific idea.
他想在太空领域投资
He wanted to invest in space
即使这对他来讲不是一个很好的投资
even although it was probably not a good investment for him.
他就是喜欢这种我个人认为很极客的风格
He just liked the idea I think personally being a nerd.
但是如果没有他的话 Vulacn Ventures基本上停止了对平流层发射系统的投资
But without him, Vulcan Ventures essentially stopped funding Stratolaunch
而平流层发射系统也被因此嘲笑为
and Stratolaunch were laughed with the world's biggest aircraft
可以飞的世界上最大的飞机
which they did prove would fly
但是不能带着任何东西飞
but they didn't have anything that they could fly on it.
这就是我们目前所了解到的东西
So yeah this is what has brought us today
这也促使我(在KSP里)玩了下这个航天器
and this has brought us to me flying this thing around.
它最后工作得其实挺不错
It actually works pretty well in the end.
尽管我降落时摔了
Although I'm having a hard time landing it.
但是当然了 我只花了5分钟来设计
But of course I designed that in five minutes.
而他们花了好几年来设计平流层发射系统
They spent years designing Stratolaunch.
问题在于他们能否让卫星落地
But the question remains can they stick the metaphorical landing
这样才能让大鹏继续存在下去
and bring a reason for the Roc to exist.
这当然很好
It would be great.
我觉得它是一个美丽的飞机
I think it's a beautiful aircraft.
我觉得这是一个惊人的技术
I think it's an amazing work of technology
而让人遗憾的是我们找不到它的应用
and it's a shame that we haven't got an application for it.
所以我们希望能看到这个庞然大物发射高超音速航天器吧
So here's hoping we see hypersonic aircraft launch from this monster
因为这将令人惊叹
because that would be amazingly cool
而且实际上这会比停在博物馆里强无数倍
and in fact infinitely times cooler than the alternative which is this ends up parked in a museum.
我是Scott Manley 祝你安全飞行
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
[Music]
[音乐]